<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some few questions concerning the Oath of allegiance propos'd by a Catholick gentleman in a letter to a person of learning and honour.</title>
            <author>Walsh, Peter, 1618?-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38929</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18196310</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18196310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1135:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some few questions concerning the Oath of allegiance propos'd by a Catholick gentleman in a letter to a person of learning and honour.</title>
                  <author>Walsh, Peter, 1618?-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: A.G.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Peter Walsh by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 35.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106996:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME FEVV QUESTIONS CONCERNING THE OATH OF ALLEGIANCE, Propos'd by a Catholick Gentleman In a LETTER to a Perſon of Learning and Honour.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MATH. VII. VII.</bibl>Quaerite &amp; Invenietis.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106996:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106996:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Thouſand to one now you'l be inquiring, who is the Author? Pardon me, if I frankly anſwer, what need you care? Judge of the Veniſon, and never trouble your ſelf with asking whence it comes. 'Tis a ſhort Book, though a long Letter; and when you have perus'd a period or two, if you like it, you may read on; if not, lay it down, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take your ſelf to ſome better buſineſſe: only oblige me with this favour, if you allow not what I have done; teach me what I ſhould have done. This is my caſe.</p>
            <p>Me thought I ſaw the truth hang clearly on my ſide, while I conſider'd only the weights which each hand laid in the ballance; but the Number of thoſe who strove by plain force to pull down the Other, a little mov'd, I confeſſe, and ſhak'd my Scale: yet I eaſily recover'd my former ſteddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when I reflected on the Moment one ſolid Reaſon has, compar'd to a multitude even of the graveſt Opiners: But then they ſhrewdly heav'd at me again; Why ſhould not the Many be preſum'd to have Reaſon, as well as the Few? againſt which, thus much, at leaſt, I had to ſay, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſomewhat more to think; That ſince either too ſtrong an Intereſt, or too weak a Courage, or too ſlight an Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, may juſtly be ſuſpected as the general cauſe of spreading that Opinion, I hop'd my inferiourneſſe in number would not be able to work me any great prejudice with thoſe who fairly compar'd my advantages in other reſpects; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if we remember the diligences perpetually us'd for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Eccleſiaſtical Prerogatives; by advancing ſtill favourable Tenets, and prohibiting the contrary; while the good Lay-Princes ſeldome provide ſo carefully for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and where they do, ſuch tender Doctrines grow ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſlowly, and if they chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to take a little, yet, for want of depth, ſoon wither away.</p>
            <p>Nor is my Party ſo few as not to be conſiderable: If three or four Doctors, nay perhaps One, who has well ſtudied the Point, can make an Opinion ſafe; What may we ſay where a greater
<pb facs="tcp:106996:3"/> number of whole Univerſities engage their Judgements? Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities equal to the beſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> who on purpoſe ſtudyed and disputed the Queſtion, and having ſeriouſly ponder'd both what Popes had done, and Councils had defin'd, and all kind of Authors had written, at laſt unanimouſly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and decreed what this following <hi>Letter</hi> intends to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>When I was thus by Reaſon and Authority ſatisfied in my own mind, ſtill there remain'd a Scruple to publiſh it; for though I ſuppoſe my ſelf ſecure of a Truth, what have I to do, being a private Man, to tell it to others; especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Thoſe who are infinitely more competent Judges than I? But as again I beg your Counſel, let me again tell you my condition; I obſerv'd, that moſt of the Perſons, from whom we might expect ſuch diſcourſes, were either diverted by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imployments, or for particular conſiderations unwilling to meddle with This: On the other ſide I conſider'd how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Charity it were to be the occaſion of ſetling clearly ſo important a Doctrine, that we might hang no longer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Heaven and Earth, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Ceſar,</hi> ſuſtain'd only by the ſlippery running-knot of <hi>Probability,</hi> which will be fast or looſe, as the Caſuist pleaſes, especially if the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters endeavours ſhould be bleſt with ſo happy ſucceſſe, as to give the leaſt contribution towards the attainment of a more condeſcending Form of Oath; wherein, the <hi>manner</hi> of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion being a little chang'd, every ſyllable of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> might entirely be retain'd; many of the better-tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd Refuſers being obſerv'd to ſcruple more at ſome Phraſe, than at any Thing in the Oath.</p>
            <p>This ſtrongly carryed me to wiſh the Work done; but my own unqualifiedneſſe extremely diſcourag'd me from doing it: At laſt, ſeeing my Independence on any (as to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar expectations) was a Circumſtance very ſuitable to ſuch an undertaking, and in very few to be found, my thoughts weary of ſtrugling one with another, ſat down and reſted, upon this Concluſion, That to propoſe my Senſe by way of <hi>Quaeres</hi> could not be eſteem'd preſumptuous, ſince e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very fool has wit enough to ask Queſtions, and I have left for others, the Wiſe man's part, to anſwer them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106996:3"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="oath">
               <body>
                  <head>THE OATH OF ALLEGIANCE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I A. B.</hi> Do truly and ſincerely Acknowledge, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, Testify, and Declare in my Conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and the World, That our Soveraign Lord King <hi>CHARLES</hi> is lawful and rightful King of this Realm, and of all other his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Majeſties Dominions and Countries; And that the Pope, neither of himſelf, nor by any Authority of the Church or See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other means, with any other, hath any Power or Authority to depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe of any of his Majeſties Kingdomes or Dominions, or to diſcharge any of his Subjects of their Allegiance and Obedience to his Majeſty, or to give licence or leave to any of them to bear Arms, raiſe Tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to his Majeſties Perſon, State, or Government, or to any of his Majeſties Subjects, within his Majeſties Dominions.</p>
                  <p>Alſo I do Swear from my heart, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Declaration, or ſentence of Excommunication, or Deprivation made or granted, or to be made or grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the Pope, or his Succeſsors, or by any Authority derived, or pretended to be derived from him, or his See, againſt the ſaid King, his Heires, or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or any Abſolution of the ſaid Subjects from their Obedience, I will bear Faith and true Allegiance to his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106996:4"/> Majeſty, his Heires and Succeſsors, and him and them will defend to the uttermost of my power, againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt his, or their Perſons, their Crown, and Dignity, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence, or Declaration, or otherwiſe; And will do my best endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſcloſe, and make known unto his Majeſty; his Heires and Succeſsors, all Treaſons, and Traiterous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, which I ſhall know or hear of, to be againſt him, or any of them.</p>
                  <p>And I do further ſwear, that I do from my heart ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, detest and abjure, as Impious and Haeretical, this damnable Doctrine, and Poſition; That Princes which be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Excommunicated, or Deprived by the Pope, may be depoſed, or murthered by their Subjects, or any other whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>And I do believe, and in my Conſcience am reſolved, that neither the Pope, nor any Perſon whatſoever, hath power to abſolve me of this Oath, or any part thereof, which I acknowledge by good and full Authority to be lawfully miniſtred unto me, and do renounce all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons and Diſpenſations to the contrary. And all theſe things I do plainly and ſincerely Acknowledge and Swear, according to theſe expreſs words by me ſpoken, and according to the plain, and common Senſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſame words, without any Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Mental Evaſion, or ſecret Reſervation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
                  <p>And I do make this Recognition, and Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, heartily, willingly, and truly, upon the true Faith of a Chriſtian. <hi>So help me God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:106996:4"/>
               <head>THE LETTER.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AS your Civility has taught me, I may have any thing of you for asking, ſo my own Experience teaches me, nothing is more eaſy than to ask; Unleſs it be, to doubt, or to be ignorant; two qualities ſo common, and ſo little implying any conceit of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency in their Owner, that I hope you will neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me of Preſumption, while I only ſeek what I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs not to know; nor of Imprudence, while I ſeek where I know I am moſt like to find. Your peircing Eye has both read what others ſay, and penetrated what they maintain; Your generous mind neither hopes nor fears can corrupt; and, if they could, your happy Condition ſecures you from both: To you therefore I confidently come, and without any farther Compliments, which you are too wiſe to expect, and I too uncourtly to give, I humbly deſire your free and ſpeedy judgment, in theſe few Seaſonable and Important <hi>Questions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some ſay the Pope, by direct and immediate ſentence, can depoſe Princes; Others, he can only Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate directly, and depoſe by Conſequence. Some ſay, he can depoſe only Princes Subject to the Church; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Infidels too. Some ſay, he has power to do this only in order to Spirituals; Others, abſolutely without that Reſtriction. Some ſay, the Crime muſt be Hereſy, or Apoſtacy; Others extend his Juriſdiction to more, and even all Caſes. And there are who ſay, He cannot depoſe at all, neither any of theſe ways, nor <unclear>for</unclear> any of theſe Perſons, nor for any of theſe Cauſes.</p>
               <p>In favour of which laſt Poſition (not to ſpeak of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Authors) 'twas my fortune lately to meet with a Cenſure of the <hi>Faculty</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſome publick and ſolemn Decrees made by that, and divers other Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of <hi>France;</hi> Of which, the better to entitle my ſelf to beg your Judgment, I here ſend you a ſhott Extract; On purpoſe omitting the French King and Parliaments Prohibition and Arreſts, as Lay-arguments, of little, and perhaps too little weight, with ſome that diſpute this point.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="decree">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106996:5"/>
                     <head>A <hi>Decree</hi> of the Univerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> made by the Rector, Deans, Proctors, and Batchelers of the ſaid Univerſity, in a General Aſſembly had on the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> 1626. at the <hi>Matutin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT having been repreſented by the Rector, that the ſacred Faculty of <hi>Theology,</hi> moved as well by their ardent zeal and fidelity towards the Church, his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, and his Kingdomes; as alſo by the true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love which they bear to Right and Juſtice, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein the illuſtrious Examples left by their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors in like Caſes, upon mature Examination of a certain Latine book, intituled, <hi>A Treatiſe of Hereſy, Schiſm, Apoſtacy, &amp;c. and of the Popes power in order to the puniſhment of thoſe Crimes,</hi> Printed at <hi>Rome, 1625.</hi> had in the 30. and 31. Chapters of Hereſy, found theſe Propoſitions; <hi>That the Pope may with temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments chaſtize Kings and Princes, deſpoſe, and deprive them of their Eſtates and Kingdomes, for the Crime of Hereſy, and exempt their Subjects from the obedience due to them; and that this cuſtome has been always practis'd in the Church, &amp;c.</hi> and thereupon had by a publick, juſt, and legal Sentence, on the <hi>4th.</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> Cenſured theſe Propoſitions of that pernicious book, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd the Doctrine therein contain'd, as <hi>New, Falſe, Erronious, contrary to the Law of God, rendring odious the Papal Dignity, opening a gap to Schiſm, derogative to the Soveraign Authority of Kings, which depends on God alone, retarding the Converſion of Infidels, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Princes, diſturbing the publick Peace, tending to the ruine of Kingdomes, and Republicks, diverting Subjects from the obedience due to their Soveraigns, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitating them into Faction, Rebellion, Sedition, and even to commit Paricides on the ſacred Perſons of their Princes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Rector, Deans, Proctors, Batchelers, and whole Univerſity have made this Decree; That the ſacred Faculty of <hi>Theology</hi> ought highly to be commended, for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106996:5"/> having given a judgment ſo Pious, ſo Religious, ſo Whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, againſt ſo wicked and dangerous a Doctrine; For having ſo opportunely held forth to the whole Church, but eſpecially to all <hi>France,</hi> the clear light of Antient and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Doctrine; For having ſo gloriouſly follow'd the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious generoſity of their Predeceſſors, and performed a task, not only becoming their particular Profeſſion to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the truth, but deſerving the Imitation even of the whole Univerſity it ſelf.</p>
                     <p>And to obſtruct altogether the very entrance of this new and pernicious Doctrine, and cauſe all thoſe who now are, or hereafter ſhall be Members of this Univerſity, or merit promotion to any Degree therein, to remember for ever to form and regulate their Opinions according to the judgment pronounced by that ſacred Faculty, and keep at utmoſt diſtance from the Doctrine ſo juſtly proſcrib'd, and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one in particular may fly, deteſt, &amp; abhor it, and as well in publick, as private, Combate, Confute, and Convince its falſity: They do decree, that in the next ſolemn Proceſſion, as alſo annually in the Aſſembly for the Proceſſion general, immediately after opening the Schools in the month of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> this Cenſure ſhall publickly be read by the Proctor of the Univerſity (the firſt buſineſs, nothing to intervene) and recorded in the Regiſters of each Faculty, and Nation; and that two Copies hereof, written and ſigned by the hand of the Clerk of the ſacred Faculty of <hi>Theology,</hi> ſhall be kept in the Common Records of the Univerſity, and the like number be ſent as ſoon as may be to all Superiours of Colleges, and Houſes, to the end all poſſible care and diligence be us'd to ſecure all thoſe who frequent, or reſide in the ſaid Colleges, from the corruption and poyſon of this pernicious Doctrine; and that they never give way that any Perſon whatſoever preſume to ſay or do any thing contrary to what has ſo wiſely been determined and ordain'd by that ſacred Faculty.</p>
                     <p>If any Doctor, Profeſſor, Maſter of Arts or Scholar reſiſt and diſobey, or go about in any ſort by word or writing, on any cauſe or pretence whatſoever, to offer at the leaſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, or make the leaſt oppoſition againſt this ſo laudable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106996:6"/> and legal a Cenſure, let him for a note of Infamy and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny be expel'd &amp; depriv'd of his Degree, Faculty, &amp; Rank, by a ſentence that may for ever cut off all hope of admittance.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Quintaine, <hi>Scribe of the Univerſity.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Cenſure of the Faculty of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> dated <hi>4th. April</hi> 1626. I omit, becauſe recited at large in this of the Univerſity.</p>
               <p>The like Decrees on the ſame occaſion, and againſt the ſame Doctrine (That the Pope can puniſh Kings with temporal puniſhments, depoſe them and deprive them of their Kingdomes and Eſtates, &amp;c.) were made by theſe ſeveral Univerſities following; All which have lately been printed at <hi>Paris</hi> in a <hi>Collection of divers Acts, Cenſures, and Decrees as well of the Univerſity, as of the Faculty of</hi> Theology <hi>of</hi> Paris.</p>
               <p>By the Univerſity of <hi>Caen,</hi> aſſembled in the Convent of S. <hi>Francis, 7. May</hi> 1626.</p>
               <p>By the Univerſity of <hi>Rheims,</hi> the four Facultyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſembled in the Chapel of S. <hi>Patrice, 18. May</hi> 1626.</p>
               <p>By the Univerſity of <hi>Tholouze,</hi> the Rector and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of all the Facultyes being aſſembled in S. <hi>Thoma</hi>'s School at the <hi>Dominicans, 23. May</hi> 1626.</p>
               <p>By the Univerſity of <hi>Poitiers,</hi> aſſembled at the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans, 26. June</hi> 1626.</p>
               <p>By the Univerſity of <hi>Valence,</hi> aſſembled in the great Hall, 14. <hi>July</hi> 1626.</p>
               <p>By the Univerſity of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> aſſembled at the <hi>Carms, 16. July</hi> 1626.</p>
               <p>By the Univerſity of <hi>Bourges,</hi> all the Deans and Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors Regent of all the Faculties aſſembled by the Rector, 25. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1626.</p>
               <p>By all which the ſaid Doctrine was Condemn'd as <hi>Falſe, Erronious, Contrary to the Word of God, Pernicious, Seditious, and Deteſtable.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106996:6"/>
               <p>AND now, ſince ſo many, ſo famous Univerſities have unanimouſly, and ſolemnly, and deeply con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demn'd this Poſition (That Popes can puniſh Princes temporally) and all this without conſtraint, volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily delivering their free judgments, unmenaced by their King, unconcern'd in ſelf-preſervation: The firſt Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion wherein I intreat your aſſiſtance, is</p>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <head>I. Why we, when our Laws ſo threatningly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and our All is ſo nearly concern'd, may not ſafely and uncenſurably profeſs as much as They?</head>
                  <p>AND I beg of you a more ſatisfactory anſwer, than, that the Pope in prudence forbears the French, becauſe their party is numerous, and learn'd, and united, and Perſons of heart and courage; for (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to obſerve the advantage this very Objection offers, by confeſſing ſo great Authority againſt that pretended Power) I ſhould eaſily ſecure my ſelf with this reply, that were not their Caſe, in it ſelf, at leaſt tolerable, all thoſe fair qualities could never juſtify the Popes ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to condemn them. Their Tenets then clearly are in themſelves conſiſtent with Faith and Catholick Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and 'tis a Conſideration meerly prudential, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch proceedings ought to be Cenſur'd or no; which naturally leads me to my ſecond <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="question">
                  <head>II. If there be reaſons enow to turn the Eye of Authority quite away from ſeeing what whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities ſo openly avow in the face of the world: are there not enow to Connive at us, who are but a few, and act privately, and not without the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing plea of extreme neceſſity?</head>
                  <p>HEre, Your firſt thoughts perhaps may offer you this diſtinction, That in <hi>England</hi> 'tis requir'd to renounce the Doctrine as <hi>Impious and Heritical,</hi> while
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106996:7"/> the French condemn it only as <hi>Falſe, Erroneous, Contrary to the Word of God, Pernicious, Seditious, and Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> But I appeal to your ſecond thoughts, and ask,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="question">
                  <head>III. Are thoſe two words, <hi>Impious and Heretical,</hi> ſo vaſtly different in their true and natural ſenſe, from the other half dozen, <hi>Falſe, Erroneous Contrary to the word of God, Pernicious, Seditious, Deteſtable,</hi> that all theſe ſix may voluntarily be affirm'd; and both thoſe, or at least, one of them, whatever ruine attends, muſt neceſſarily be deny'd?</head>
                  <p>IF we be oblig'd, as ſure we are, to anſwer in the ſenſe of our Propoſers, and they mean no more by <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical</hi> (as the very Principles of their Religion, beſides other Arguments, ſufficiently aſſure us) than <hi>Erroneous, and Contrary to the word of God;</hi> I hope this third <hi>Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion</hi> will prove no invincible difficulty; For, is not what's Contrary to the word of God, Contrary to Faith; and what's Contrary to Faith, Heretical? Eſpecially ſince among our ſelves we muſt find a larger ſenſe for <hi>Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> than that which ſeverely meaſures its conceiv'd ſtricteſt notion; We muſt find a ſenſe wherein the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Antipodes</hi> was antiently Heretical, and the Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Earth, or at leaſt the Standing of the Sun is ſo now; one of which the <hi>Qualificatori</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>Galileo</hi>'s Condemnation, Cenſur'd as Abſurd, Falſe, &amp;c. the Other, as formally Heretical; We muſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> find a ſenſe that may juſtify not only our diſputing Schoolmen, who often on ſlighter grounds, cry out <hi>Hereſy</hi> one againſt another; but the publick Cenſors of Books, and Qualifiers of Opinions, who every day reject many Doctrines as Heretical, without intending to divide Communion from the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inteiners; Nay, we muſt find a ſenſe that may agree with the words of the Pope himſelf,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106996:7"/> in his Prohibitive <hi>Brief</hi> of this very Oath, which, he ſayes, <hi>contains many things contrary to Faith and Salvation;</hi> and what can we imagin ſhould be thoſe <hi>Many,</hi> if the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of his Prince-depoſing power be not counted for One? yet poſſibly neither It, nor any of theſe I have mention'd are, in preciſe ſcholaſtic rigor, Heretical: But Uſe and Cuſtome being the Rule of Speech, I cannot ſee it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, why we alone in ſo Important an Occaſion, ſhould be denyed that latitude of ſenſe, which we know is ſo frequently, and ſo juſtifiably allow'd to all the world.</p>
                  <p>To reconcile more clearly this difference, I conceive the common Diſtinction of <hi>Material</hi> and <hi>Formal</hi> Hereſy very uſeful: According to the firſt ſenſe, whatever is now Heretical, alwayes was ſo in its inward nature; the Deciſion of the Church operating only by way of Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the formerly believ'd Truth, and Extenſion of the Obligation to new Subjects, adding perhaps expreſs Menaces of <hi>Anathema, &amp;c.</hi> to obſtinate Diſſenters, which every one is juſtly preſum'd to be, that ſubmits not to the known determination of the Univerſal Church.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond ſenſe many Tenets are not yet Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, which may in time become ſo: Even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly falſe and flattering Poſition, That the Pope is <hi>direct</hi> Univerſal King over all the World, is not yet (the Church not uſing to interpoſe Her Authority, till the Deciſion be neceſſary) condemn'd as Heretical; though certainly, none that pretend to the leaſt degree of true Loyalty, but are ready to abjure ſo damnable a Doctrine, as worſe than Impious, worſe than Heretical. 'Tis evidently therefore enough to verifie my forſwearing ſuch an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour as Heretical, if in it ſelf it be notably miſchievous, without expecting till the Church can meet, and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Her Canonical Sentence upon it.</p>
                  <p>Though this Example of ſo many Univerſities be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to decide the Queſtion, in that they renounc'd this pretended Power; and more than ſufficient, to juſtifie us, in that they did it freely: Yet to propoſe an Inſtance agreeing, even in the point of fear too, with ours;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106996:8"/> I ſhall not forbear to ſay there was a numerous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Party in <hi>France</hi> (no leſſe than the whole Body of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi>) whoſe Judgement was known to differ from That of the Univerſities as much as Any, and more than moſt of Ours here, yet rather than expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Inconveniences, and their Intereſts to Danger; they publikely ſubſcrib'd the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> Cenſures; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly condemn'd this King-dethroning Power, as Falſe, Erronious, contrary to the Word of God, Pernicious, Seditious, and Deteſtable.</p>
                  <p>How this ſo ſolemn Subſcription, againſt what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had formerly held either as <hi>altogether,</hi> or at leaſt as <hi>almoſt</hi> an Article of Faith, was underſtood at <hi>Rome,</hi> I know not: that it was actually done in <hi>France,</hi> I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent will not be deny'd: that it was commanded, we need no other Evidence than the Arreſt it ſelf of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> dated 17. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1626. wherein 'tis Order'd <hi>That the Prieſts and Scholars of</hi> Clermont, <hi>and of the other two Houſes which the Jeſuits have in</hi> Paris, <hi>ſhould within three days ſubſcribe the Cenſure made by the Faculty of</hi> Sorbonne: <hi>and within two months procure Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials of the like Subſcription from every Provincial, and Rector, and from ſix of the Antients of every College of their Society in</hi> France.</p>
                  <p>Nor can it be ſaid, this Subſcription relates only in general to <hi>Sautarellus</hi>'s Book, ſince it particularly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the whole Cenſure of <hi>Sorbonne;</hi> whereof one and the firſt branch is directly, and in moſt expreſſe terms, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Popes <hi>Power to puniſh Kings Temporally, to Depoſe, &amp;c.</hi> If this be true, of which I know not the leaſt reaſon to doubt,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="question">
                  <head>IV. Why is it not Lawful for Engliſh Catholicks to be Loyal to their Prince, as far as the French to Theirs? Why is it not tolerable in Lay-men here to diſavow, what the stricteſt Religious there open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemn? Strictest, I mean, in maintaining, and extending the Popes Prerogatives, and ſo moſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106996:8"/> pertinent to our Queſtion: Shall Humane Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives be allow'd their place with Them who renounce the World, and not with thoſe who live in it?</head>
                  <p>IF any ſhall here pretend to diſtinguiſh between a ſimple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ubſcription, which only was requir'd of the French Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, &amp; a down right Oath, which is exacted of us; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think but they proceed with too much ſcruple; ſince certainly no ſincere and generous honeſty will ſolemnly and deliberately atteſt under his hand, what he will not in due circumſtances ſwear to be true: and indeed, for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Perſons, who actually ſtill reflect on the preſence of God, what difference can there be, between calling Him in a form of words to witneſſe what they ſay, eſpecially with ſuch Solemnity and Deliberation; and beleeving him continually in their hearts to witneſs not only what they ſay, but what they think?</p>
                  <p>And now were I demanded a reaſon, why ſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and wiſe a Body ſhould act ſo differently in the ſame cauſe but different Countries; I could only return this conjectural Anſwer; that being wary and prudent perſons, they could not but ſee the Concerns they hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi>France</hi> by refuſing to Subſcribe, far more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, than what they ventur'd at <hi>Rome</hi> by Subſcribing: whereas in <hi>England,</hi> all they can forfeit by declining the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> (being themſelves but few, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Engagements of Colleges and Foundations) is perhaps of leſſe eſteem with them, than the intereſt of their Univerſal Body at <hi>Rome,</hi> whence ſo many advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages are continually deriv'd to the reſt of their Society.</p>
                  <p>When I have taken leave to ſuppoſe for True, That a <hi>certain</hi> general Rule, is to be obſerv'd, notwithſtanding an Exception that's <hi>incertain;</hi> I may eaſily hope your leave to ask this fifth Queſtion;</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="question">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106996:9"/>
                  <head>V. If the Precept of Obedience to Kings in Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals be a certain Catholick Doctrine, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception (unleſſe the Pope depoſe) be incertain; whether the Precept does not still Oblige notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that Exception?</head>
                  <p>ANd however ſuch a power may by ſome be held ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatively probable, yet, as to any Execution, 'tis practically <hi>no Power</hi> at all, againſt one in poſſeſſion; and conſequently may be ab ur'd as <hi>ſuch:</hi> he that has only a ſpeculatively probable Commiſſion to take away my life, has none at all actually to <hi>do</hi> it: and every one will ſurely agree that to diſpoſſeſſe a King is of infinitely more miſchievous Conſequence than to kill a private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; Witneſs the horrid miſeries that follow'd the Depoſition of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, by <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh; the firſt Pope, and firſt Emperour that ever engag'd ſo far in that kind of quarrel; a quarrel wherein both ſides endur'd for a long time unſpeakable Calamities, both ſides ſtriving with all extremity of paſſion and fury to ruine one another.</p>
                  <p>Our Allegiance to Kings, and Their Title to our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance being both, in their natures, antecedent to Baptiſm; For the relation of King and Subject is by Birth, and the quality of Chriſtian by Adoption;</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="question">
                  <head>VI. How can the Superinduced ſpiritual Obligation diminiſh the Civil, when no ſuch Condition is contain'd either in Baptiſm, Catechiſm, or Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith; Eſpecially ſince we are baptiz'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Communion of Believers, not of Opiners?</head>
                  <p>TIS true, both Prince &amp; people, do by their God-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Baptiſm renounce the world, the fleſh, &amp; the devil: but neither of them make any promiſe to forfeit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106996:9"/> their Crowns or Eſtates to the Pope, if they break their word. Nay, even Popes themſelves, in the primitive times, were temporally Subject to the Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours both before and after their Converſion: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſince <hi>the Christian Law,</hi> by the Judgement of all, <hi>deprives none of their Right,</hi> if they were Subject before the Princes Converſion, they muſt needs continue ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>Nor can I ſee (and in this every Reader is concern'd) why the Pope if once admitted to diſpenſe with Subjects Allegiance to their Prince, may not diſcharge the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants too from paying Rents to their Landlords, and Debters from their Obligations to their Creditors, as often as He ſhall Judge the Intereſt of Religion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it. Nay, by the ſame reaſon, driven a ſtep or two farther; why may not every Biſhop in his Dioceſs, and every Curate in his Pariſh pretend a Right, <hi>radically</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in his Dignity, to diſpoſe of all our Eſtates in Order to the good of our Souls; and that 'tis only either the hard-heartedneſs of Lay-Magiſtrates to hinder it from ſhooting forth into branches; or the Wiſdome of the Supreme Spiritual Magiſtrate to reſerve the whole fruit to Himſelf?</p>
                  <p>Already by my own reflexions I am fully ſatisfied that a Diſpenſation (ſhould any ſuch be pretended) with the <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance, would be no Diſpenſation with the <hi>Duty</hi> of Allegiance: The Duty being Antecedent to the Oath, and Independent of it, and only Confirm'd, not Created by it: and therefore as to this point, I find no neceſſity of giving you any trouble.</p>
                  <p>But in the next Queſtion I muſt humbly beſpeak your pardon, becauſe I fear my boldneſs may need it: 'Tis a Caſe I never have yet ſeen well examin'd, and therefore more doubtingly propoſe it.</p>
                  <p>The Graveſt Aſſertors of the Popes indirect power to depoſe Princes, warily confine Him to two Caſes; which they call <hi>Hereſy</hi> and <hi>Apoſtaſy:</hi> And, as by <hi>Apostate</hi> they muſt neceſſarily mean One that has been a Catholick, and is <hi>quite</hi> faln away from Chriſtianity; So ſurely by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106996:10"/> 
                     <hi>Heretick</hi> they ſhould proportionably underſtand One that has been a Catholick, and is <hi>in part</hi> faln away from the Faith: This Conſideration, I confeſſe, bred in me a ſcruple, I am not able, without your help to ſatisfie: How a Proteſtant Baptiz'd into the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be held oblig'd to the poſitive Laws of another Church; to which, neither himſelf, nor his God-fathers, promis'd any Obedience: his Baptiſm indeed confers Grace, and adopts him into the State of Salvation; but why ſhould he be counted ſubject to the Government of a Communion quite oppoſite to That into which he is Baptiz'd? does a Proteſtant commit a Mortal Sin every time he eats Fleſh on a Faſting day, or omits to hear Maſſe on a Holyday, when neither Maſſe, nor perhaps that Holyday is allow'd by his Church?</p>
                  <p>We know, whoever loves God above all things, is in the State of Salvation, but not of External Communion, till he actually ſubmit to it; and me thinks it ſeems ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, that I ſhould be interpreted to ſubmit to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a Church of ſuch a Diſcipline, by my very being Baptiz'd into a Church of a contrary one.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, Followers of thoſe who began the Diviſion are not in the ſame form of Church-Condemnation with thoſe who began it; much leſſe when they are born of ſuch Parents, and bred up in a Country where ſuch Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets have ſo long and uncontrolledly been eſtabliſh'd, that many perhaps may hold them, without being <hi>guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of holding them; Wherefore I humbly intreat your Learning to inſtruct me,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="question">
                  <head>VII. Whether You have read any Authors that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely ſay, a Magiſtrate ſo Circumſtantiated may be Depos'd by the Pope, eſpecially ſince I remember not one Instance, Ancient or Modern, of any ſuch Prince ſo treated?</head>
                  <p>THE Examples of depoſing Princes being without any certain Rule, ſometimes by the Pope, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the Nobility, ſometimes by the People, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106996:10"/> by an Eminent Subject, ſometimes by a powerful Stranger; And the ground pretended, being ſometimes Religion, ſometimes ſome other Cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> give me leave to conſult your judgement,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="question">
                  <head>VIII. Whether thoſe Examples may not all be reſolv'd, Either by the General Anſwer, that <hi>Fact makes no Right;</hi> Or, that they were practis'd without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ordinary and acknowledg'd Juriſdiction; but only by way of common Reaſon and natural Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which teaches us in extremities to caſt about and relieve our ſelves, in the beſt and hopefullest way we can, according to our Circumſtances?</head>
                  <p>FOr though by this Almighty Maxime of <hi>Extreme and Lawleſſe neceſſity,</hi> even Popes themſelves, as well as other Governors, have ſometimes been depoſed; yet I clearly believe neither Popes, nor Councils, nor Kings, nor Nobles, nor People, nor Strangers, have any Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant Commiſſion from Heaven, that conſtitutes in any of them a Formal and Authorotative Tribunal to decide Juriſdictionally who ſhall be Pope or King.</p>
                  <p>To make this diſtinction (on which the whole contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy chiefly depends) unmiſtakably plain and evident; let me parallel the grand Inſtances of Popes and Kings, with the litle ones of private perſons: when we ſay, as I think every Chriſtian does, that 'tis Impious and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical to hold, One Neighbour can take away the life of another, though he never ſo much deſerve it; in Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to what power do we ſpeak? is it not to that kind of power which is ordinarily Created by Commiſſion? can we be fairly interpreted to mean ſome odd extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant caſe of abſolute neceſſity to defend our own lives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his otherwiſe unavoidable Aſſaults? So when we ſpeak of a Power and Authority to depoſe Kings, we are plainly to underſtand a Power and Authority veſted in <hi>St. Peter</hi> and his Succeſſors by Commiſſion from Chriſt:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106996:11"/> This and this only, I conceive, is the Authority we are commanded to abjure; and unleſſe ſuch a Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion be ſhewn, I cannot ſee why to aſſert ſuch a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Pope is not Impious and Heretical, as much and far more than the inſtance of private Murther: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>Oath</hi> ſo particularly expreſſing its chief intent to be the excluſion of the Popes pretences, and preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the miſchiefs naturally apprehended from the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and all-Commanding Juriſdiction of a Foreiner.</p>
                  <p>Having perus'd ſome Authors who confidently ſay, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Orthodox Divine maintain'd this tranſcendent power in the Pope, nor ever any ſuch practices appear'd for above a thouſand years after Chriſt; though the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians long before that time had both ſtrength enough to do it, if they had had a Will; and Zeal enough to have will'd it, if they had thought it lawful: I cannot but ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect this Doctrine of Novelty, till you be pleas'd to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form me,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="question">
                  <head>IX. What Eminent Writers there are, in the first thouſand years after Chriſt, who expreſly hold this Tenet of the Popes Authority to Depoſe Princes?</head>
                  <p>THis I am apt to conceive ſo much the more impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable to be found; becauſe neither <hi>S. Tho.</hi> nor <hi>Card<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Bellarmine</hi> cite any Antienter Authors than <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the ſeventh, whoſe Papacy is of a younger date than that we ſpeak of: Much younger yet is the Council of <hi>Lateran;</hi> nor can it with the leaſt colour of truth be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg'd for any more than a Canonical Conſtitution; and perhaps not ſo much, till the difficulties concerning it be clear'd, which I leave to the Doctors, and only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, 'tis at beſt no more; elſe the Defenders of Papal Depoſition were bound to believe its Decree in this point as an Article of Faith, and condemn the French Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities as Heretical, and ſeparate from their Communion: if then it be only an Eccleſiaſtical Canon, 'tis well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough known ſuch Laws are not Obliging, but where
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106996:11"/> they are receiv'd, and where they are received, may on juſt grounds be again rejected. However, even where that Canon is admitted (if any where it be) no fair In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter can extend it to reach ſo high as Soveraign Princes, to whom this reſpect is generally by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts eſteem'd due, that unleſſe They be expreſly nam'd, they are not by implication underſtood to be comprehended in any penal or reſtrictive clauſe, a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility allow'd even to Cardinals, whom I cannot think a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſintereſſed Conſiderer will preferr before Kings.</p>
                  <p>As for reaſon, which I confeſs, where 'tis evident, needs no Antiquity to gain my aſſent; I have not met with any that bids ſo fair towards ſatisfaction, as this argument.</p>
                  <p>If the Ends be ſubordinate to one another, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultyes are.</p>
                  <p>But the End of Civil Power (temporal happineſs) is ſubordinate to the End of Spiritual Power (eternal happineſs.)</p>
                  <p>Therefore the Civil Power is ſubordinate to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual.</p>
                  <p>Let all this be ſuppos'd as true (though there want not diſtinctions, by which ſome endeavour to relieve themſelves in this point too) I only enquire how this Spiritual Superiour muſt proceed, when the Temporal Magiſtrate intolerably miſdemeans himſelf; &amp; I think He is confin'd, as his very <hi>Name</hi> imports, to Spiritual pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as ſuſpenſion from Sacraments, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But that, they'l ſay is not ſufficient, nor the Church compleatly furniſh'd with means proportionate to its end, unleſs it can depoſe a Prince that deſerves it. To which, I anſwer,</p>
                  <p>Firſt. The argument is of ſo wild unlimited a Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that ſhould they inſtead of <hi>Depoſe,</hi> ſay <hi>Kill,</hi> or whatever other miſchief they pleaſe to invent, they might in Rigor with the ſame Reaſon defend it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly. Though in ſome ſence it be true, the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Power is furniſh'd with all means neceſſary to its End;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106996:12"/> yet are we not oblig'd to ſay, it can remove all impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that in what method it pleaſes; Is not the Sun compleatly endued with power to ſhine, unleſs it can level mountains, and overturn for reſts that intercept its light? or, which is nearer our Caſe, has not a King ſufficient power to govern, unleſs he can puniſh his neighbour King, nay even the Pope himſelf, and that with ſpiritual penalties? In regular and ordinary Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, the regular and ordinary power both of Pope and Prince is ſufficient: in irregular and extraordinary, the very word ſignifies, they are <hi>out of Rule,</hi> and muſt be govern'd by occaſional reaſon, which allows both to Pope and Prince a juſt and equal title to provide, that Neither prejudice the Other; and this, without the Popes being Superiour to the Prince in Temporals, any more than the Prince is to the Pope in Spirituals; But, as abſolute Soveraigns, when there's no other remedy, may lawfully make war; ſo I conceive may theſe (each managing his proper weapon) and pretend only Reaſon, not Juriſdiction to juſtify their proceedings.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I ſuſpect, this plauſible argument (the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual power is furniſh'd with all means neceſſary to its end) may ſo largely be underſtood, that it will flatly be deny'd; for, is not Execution of the Magiſtrates Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, neceſſary to the end of Government? and is not a competent Force neceſſary to that Execution? why then did our all-foreſeeing <hi>Saviour</hi> not provide for this? why did he not furniſh his Supreme Lieutenant with twelve Legions of Angels, to overcome the Princes of the Earth, that will not obey his Decrees? As to this, I know no better reaſon, than that the Churches Hymn is true,</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Non eripit Mortalia,</l>
                        <l>Qui Regna dat Caeleſtia.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He does not Earthly Kings deprive,</l>
                        <l>Who came the Crown of Heaven to give.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106996:12"/>
                  <p>Beſides, may we not as well ſay, the Church is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd by <hi>Chriſt</hi> with all Offices (at leaſt all conſiderable Ones) as with all Power neceſſary to its Government? yet every one knows neither Patriarks, Primates, nor Arch-Biſhops are of divine Inſtitution, however their very being ſo canonically eſtabliſh'd in the Church, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declares their uſefulneſs and neceſſity; and their being no otherwiſe eſtabliſh'd, ſufficiently convinces the weakneſſe of the argument I am endeavouring to diſable.</p>
                  <p>If my expectations happen to fail in all theſe Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions, permit me yet to offer this ſhort Conſideration. The Poſition we are commanded to renounce as <hi>Impious,</hi> and <hi>Heretical,</hi> is this,</p>
                  <q>Princes, who are Excommunicated, or Depriv'd by the Pope, may be depos'd or murther'd by their Subjects, or any other whatſoever.</q>
                  <p>Since 'tis clear, that where the <hi>Subject</hi> of a Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in the disjunctive, unleſs the <hi>Predicate</hi> be verefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of both Members, the whole Propoſition may ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely be deny'd; it plainly follows, if to ſay a Prince Excommunicated only (not depriv'd) may be depos'd by his Subjects, be Impious and Heretical, at leaſt in the large and uſual ſenſe of that word, that the whole Propoſition is ſafely abjurable, as Impious and Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. In which diſcourſe, this only ſeems to need proof, that 'tis Heretical to ſay, a Prince Excommunicated may be depos'd by his Subjects. And firſt, I hope, it will quickly appear to be <hi>Falſe,</hi> by the very definition of <hi>Excommunication;</hi> Excommunication being <hi>a Church-Cenſure, that ſeparates from the Eccleſiaſtical Communion of the Faithful.</hi> And though by a general rule we are commanded to avoid all Hereticks, and Excommunicated Perſons, yet (beſides that, of it ſelf it reaches only to ſpiritual things, unleſs the Civil Law extend it farther) the Canoniſts give many exceptions, one is (which near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt concerns our Caſe) that of Relation; ſhall Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Wives, Parents and Children, Maſters and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106996:13"/> Servants, be bound in caſe of Excommunication to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don one another? what Confuſion would ſo raſh a Doctrine bring into the world? and is it not far worſe, if Subjects ſhall think it lawful to forſake their King, nay unlawful not to forſake him?</p>
                  <p>Thus I conceive 'tis evidently Falſe; and if once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for <hi>ſuch,</hi> its own weight will ſoon ſink it down into Impious. And what is Impious, eſpecially draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after it ſuch miſchievous effects, will eaſily be prov'd againſt the very Eſſence of the Chriſtian Law, and by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence intrinſecally Heretical. If yet you think, this opinion not ſo <hi>highly</hi> cenſurable, I beſeech you inform me,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="question">
                  <head>X. Whether any of theſe Poſitions deſerve the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of Heretical? That the Pope has a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect</hi> Dominion, both in Spirituals and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, over all the World: Or that He can deprive Kings of their lives, and paſs ſentence of death a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst them: Or againſt the lives or goods of any other Perſon? that is, whether He can make it lawful to do thoſe Acts, which, were they not Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriz'd by him, would be plain Murther, Theft, or Rebellion?</head>
                  <p>ALL theſe, every one I meet is ready to cry out on, as <hi>Impious, Hereticial,</hi> and what you will; And is the Depoſing a King a ſlighter work, than the Sequeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a private Gentleman? Or has he a weaker Title to his Crown, than a Merchant to his Shop? Either I am deceiv'd by ſome Equivocation, which I intreat you to diſcover, or elſe the Queſtion I propoſe is as clear as the Sun at Noon.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true ſome Caſes are mixt, but then me thinks it is not ſo hard a task to give each Authority its due; Can we not eaſily diſcern, what belongs to Marriage as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106996:13"/> a Sacrament, from what belongs to it, as a Civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract? Or diſtinguiſh between the Churches power to make a Baſtard incapable of Orders, and that of the Common-wealth, to make him incapable of Inheriting? Nor has the Queſtion any greater difficulty, when the Tribunals <hi>Succeſſively</hi> aſſiſt one another, as when the Eccleſiaſtics, having proceeded to the utmoſt of their Juriſdiction, deliver the Criminal to the Lay Court, there to receive ſuch further puniſhment, as his Crime deſerves, which they could not have needed, had their own power reach'd ſo far, not would they have practis'd, had they not needed it.</p>
                  <p>To conclude this point, with ſome Authority as well as Reaſon; I have read, that not only the Poſition of killing Kings was condemn'd as <hi>Impious, Heretical,</hi> and <hi>Damnable,</hi> by 141. Divines of the <hi>Faculty of</hi> Paris, in the year 1413. But ſince, in the year 1610. the ſame <hi>Faculty</hi> Decreed, <hi>That it was Seditious, Impious, and Heretical, for any Subject, Vaſſal, or Stranger, on what occaſion or pretence ſoever,</hi> Sacris Regum perſonis vim inferre, <hi>to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence to the ſacred perſons of Kings.</hi> Behold the very word <hi>Heretical,</hi> directly and formally applyed to a Poſition that in ſubſtance exceeds not Ours, unleſs we imagine a King ſo tame, that we may Depoſe him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offering him any Violence: or find ſome witty Caſuiſt, who has invented a new way of creeping out of the words (no matter for the plain and honeſt ſenſe) and by his grave Opinion, ſecure our Conſciences, that though it be Impious indeed and Heretical, to offer any force to the ſacred Perſons of Kings, yet to intercept their meat till they be ſtarv'd to death (as 'tis ſaid of one of the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi>) is abſolutely lawful, as being an <hi>omitted Caſe,</hi> and ſo not at all forbidden.</p>
                  <p>Obſerving that in this whole Controverſy, the main Bulwark wherein the Defenders of the Popes Prerogative in Temporals, fortifie themſelves, and think to pacify the Civil Powers, is a certain famous Diſtinction, whoſe plain and literal ſenſe I underſtand well enough, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106996:14"/> find in it, if impartially examin'd, a title to make ſo great an Impreſſion as is pretended; I humbly intreat your quick and ſtrong Eye, to look a little ſeriouſly into the Queſtion, and teach me,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="question">
                  <head>XI. What difference there is, as to any real effect in Government, between acknowledging a direct immediate Power in the Pope to Depoſe Princes, or only an indirect and mediate One?</head>
                  <p>IS it not almoſt all one in it ſelf, and altogether all one in miſchief, whether my eyes be beaten out with a direct ſtroke of a Tennis-Ball, or by <hi>Bricol?</hi> Are not our Laws ſtill equally Penal both to direct and indirect Offenders? will any of us allow a ſlandering tongue (than which nothing is more frequent, or more into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable) to Caluminate freely, on condition his poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous darts come only <hi>glancing,</hi> and not be level'd point-blank againſt us?</p>
                  <p>Here they perhaps will ſay, I miſtake the Caſe; For, were only the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of this Power mediate and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, they would confeſſe my ſimilitudes had ſomething of Argument, but the very <hi>Power</hi> it ſelf ſay they, is in its <hi>Intrinſick nature</hi> no more than mediate and indirect, which widens much the ſides of the diſtinction, nor do any of my Interrogations offer to confute it.</p>
                  <p>When I have firſt declar'd, I intend not to meddle with ſuch ſlender Entityes as <hi>Relations</hi> metaphyſically conſider'd; I ſhall betake my thoughts to what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more pertinent to our purpoſe, the <hi>Moral</hi> Notion; and enquire what influence on humane actions a direct Power gives its Poſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or, more than an indirect? If they anſwer, by the one He can puniſh his Inferiours, as he pleaſes, by the other not: I reply, That is the notion of an abſolute and perfectly arbitrary Government, not preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a direct Power, which not only may ſometimes be limited, but almoſt always is; has not the Emperour a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106996:14"/> direct Authority over the German Electors? Is not the Pope direct Superiour of the Chriſtian Biſhops? yet which of them can, either One or the Other, deprive or puniſh at his meer pleaſure? I they ſay, 'tis a Power as ſtrongly Commanding as the direct, but is not in the ſame line, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piritual being of a quite different Order from the Temporal; I confeſſe theſe are pretty terms to entertain ſubtile heads, and amuze ſimple ones; but to a down-right prudent Examiner, I believe they'l prove of very little ſerious Signification, nay though the Cauſes be contrary to one anothers, if they produce the ſame effect, they make with me the ſame argument. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts ſay, that Cold immediately condenſes by direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cruſhing the Body it incloſes: whereas Heat firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuates, and then draws away the ſubtiliz'd parts, and after the groſſer ſhrink together of themſelves, and ſo condenſes too, but mediately and indirectly; and theſe are words that ſound well enough; but when we come to practical application, and find that too much Sun, as well as Froſt, ſo dryes and hardens the Earth, that it choaks our ſeed, and kills our flowers, what good does our fine diſtinction? what does our <hi>Mediately</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly</hi> avail us?</p>
                  <p>Nor is the Effect only the ſame, whether the Popes power be call'd direct or indirect, ſince each way he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally dethrones the Prince; but the end to both of his direct-Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ual, and indirect-Temporal Authority is the ſame ſince He is bound to manage the laſt only, <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> and the firſt, <hi>ad Edificationem;</hi> which two phraſes ſeem to me no ill Synonimas one of another. Theſe are ſome of the reflections that have made me doubt, though there may be (and I think I ſee it) ſome Speculative difference between the two manners of Title, yet in practiſe very little, if any at all.</p>
                  <p>When all this is ſaid, and far more, (which I think not uneaſy to do) ſtill there remain two grand Objections: The Supreme Paſtor has engag'd his Authority; and our duty obliges us to obey His Commands: Our Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106996:15"/> have refus'd the Oath, and ſuffer'd for refuſing; and our honour is concern'd to follow their ſteps. To which, with your permiſſion, I offer this anſwer,</p>
                  <p>Since by the Popes forbearing the French, we evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee ſuch Prohibitions depend on particular and occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Conſiderations, not only lyable to be miſapprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by others, but to be alter'd in themſelves; certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it very ill becomes our Reverence to the Authority of the Pope, or reſpect to the Memory of our Anceſtors, to fear they would wilfully perſiſt in a diſcover'd Errour, and not change their proceedings, when they ſhould ſee the grounds on which they proceeded were chang'd.</p>
                  <p>Nor even then when the Pope's <hi>Brief</hi> forbad the Oath, did there want a juſt number of Catholicks, if my books ſay true, who humbly repreſented their Motives to his Holineſſe, why they doubted his Prohibition was not obliging, as being grounded on miſtaken and incertain Suppoſitions: A privilege permitted to all, and moſt of all to Eccleſiaſtical Subjects (who are not Govern'd by the Sword, but the Paſtoral Staff) either to obey or give good reaſon why they do not: and this, without the leaſt ſuſpition of boldly examining their Superiors Commands with the Judgement of Authority, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing only, what the meaneſt Vaſſal may Loyally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe towards the greateſt Prince, their natural Reaſon and Judgement of Diſcretion.</p>
                  <p>And here I muſt confeſſe my ſelf inclin'd to think it very probable, that the whole buſineſſe was untruly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to the Pope: for, can we doubt but <hi>Card. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> was acquainted with the Informations given to his Holyneſſe? or, that they Both agreed not in their ſence concerning our Caſe? let us then ſee what his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence ſays in his Letter to <hi>Mr. Blackwell,</hi> Arch-Prieſt of the Engliſh Clergy; where, having alleg'd that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inſtance of mingling together the Images of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, and of the falſe Gods, to entangle the Chriſtians with this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> that either they muſt bow to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and Commit Idolatry; or not bow to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106996:15"/> of high Treaſon, He ads, <hi>Tale aliquid in juramento<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> &amp;c. <hi>Some ſuch thing me thinks I ſee in this Oath they offer you, which is ſo fraudulently contriv'd, that none can profeſs their Civil Subjection to the King and Detest all Treaſon againſt Him, but he must needs perfidiouſly Renounce the Supremacy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the See Apoſtolick.</hi> And again, <hi>Nam ſi rem totam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If you will diligently examine the whole matter, you'l ſee 'tis no ſmall thing which by that Oath is brought into danger, but one of the Capital and Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Points of our Faith and Catholick Religion;</hi> And quite throughout the whole Letter He ſtill ſuppoſes the Deſign of the Framers of this Oath, how covertly ſoever they expreſſe themſelves to be; <hi>That the Authority of Head of the Church be transferr'd (as to</hi> England) <hi>from the Succeſſor of St.</hi> Peter, <hi>to the Succeſſor of</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8. Which ſtill ſo much the more evidently appears, both by his Quoting Fathers upon the general head of obeying the Pope, and acknowledging his Supremacy, as alſo by his comparing <hi>Mr. Blackwells</hi> Sin in taking the Oath, to <hi>Peters</hi> denying Chriſt, and <hi>Marcellinus</hi>'s Sacrificing to Idols; whom at leaſt in ſome part, He ſays, the Arch-Prieſt imitated. Does this Pen run as if it were guided by a Hand well inform'd? Is it not highly probable that ſuch Informations were the grounds of the Prohibition? Is it not abſolutely certain, that ſuch grounds, being pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable miſtakes, are no way ſufficient to oblige our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                  <p>Not that we have cauſe ſo much to complain of the <hi>Brief,</hi> as of them whoſe Paſſionate, and perhaps Factious Zeal procur'd it: for how can the Pope be inform'd what we <hi>Tramontani</hi> do, but by others? and how can He Judge, but as he is inform'd? ſince ſurely we are not to expect ſuch an extraordinary aſſiſtance from Heaven to guide his Hand in writing a Letter, though <hi>in Form of Brief,</hi> as ſome pretend for his defining <hi>ex Cathedrâ.</hi> Read but the <hi>Bulla Coenae,</hi> and you'l find it no impoſſible thing for the Pope to claim more, than a good Subject, much leſſe a wiſe King will give him: there he ſolemnly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicates
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106996:16"/> all Princes, who impoſe on their Subjects new <hi>Gabels</hi> without leave of the See Apoſtolick: with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other unallow'd pretences. From all which we inferr theſe two plain truths, That the Pope may miſcommand; and when he does ſo, be lawfully diſobey'd.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed ingenuouſly with you, as I hope and beg you will do with me; let us fortify this Objection with the utmoſt skill and ſtrength we can: This Act of Depoſing Kings has not only been done by Popes, but approv'd by Councils; to whoſe jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt-Authority I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe a great Reverence is due, and therefore beſeech you deal candidly with me, (for I have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any convenience to examine the circumſtances of theſe Hiſtories) did they only approve the Fact; or declare the Right? if the firſt, I ſhall without ſtaying to diſpute it, ſuppoſe the thing, for that time, well done; and only enquire, in reference to what Authority 'twas done: our <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. we know did many Acts without declaring the Title by which he did them; and the Parliaments approbation ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd them: if then they, proceeded as by a Commiſſion claim'd from Chriſt, and allow'd in a General Council, would not that make the Tenet an Article of Faith, and ſo prove too much, ſince among the Temperate it gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pretends no higher than an Opinion? but if they acted only by a Commiſſion deriv'd from Neceſſity, which having no Law, is a Law to it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Conſequence little concerns our Diſpute; who know the <hi>Pope</hi> Himſelf has been depos'd; yet neither will He admit, nor need his Depoſers pretend any Juriſdiction or Superiority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Him; 'tis enough where Neceſſity over-rules the Law, that Neceſſity Govern in its ſtead; which if true and real, may perhaps do much harm, but can do no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury.</p>
                  <p>As to the other Branch; if the Council interpos'd in declaring the Right, either they intended it as a Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then you muſt ſay 'tis <hi>of Faith,</hi> which almoſt every one denyes: or as an Eccleſiaſtical Canon, and then I muſt ſay, it binds only where receiv'd, and may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106996:16"/> be alter'd or repeal'd like other Laws, as is already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd, when we cited the Council of <hi>Lateran.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>However, in our particular Caſe, nothing is more eaſy than to Conquer the Objectors of the Popes Briefs with their own weapons; for let them tell me, are they not ready to ſwear they will faithfully ſerve their King while they live, and that <hi>notwithſtanding any Papal Diſpenſation, or whatever other Proceeding to the contrary?</hi> what ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies this, but an expreſſe renouncing all obedience to the Pope in theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ts? True ſay they, we renounce obedience, but not the acknowledgment of his Power; we will adhere to the King, though the Pope ſhould De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him; but will not ſay, he cannot Depoſe him. What wiſe and real difference (as to Government, and the practical part of humane life) can we imagine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two; <hi>I'le ſwear never to obey my Commander,</hi> and <hi>I'le ſwear he has no power to command me?</hi> Speak plain and honeſtly, and either deny his Authority, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it; this motley Hypocriſy will, I fear, offend both Pope and King, and while you diſclaim your obedience to the One, and the Authority of the Other, Neither will confide in you; Change but the Perſon, and think, what a holy religious man he would be, that ſhould ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly vow never to obey his Superiour, how loud ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he preach'd his Authority; think what a flat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction it is, of two Relatives, to kill one, and keep the other alive; think what an uncharitable madneſs it is, that the whole body of Chatholicks be expos'd to ruine, and the whole Credit of their Religion be buried in that ruine, rather than diſavow an Authority, which we are ready to ſwear we will never obey.</p>
                  <p>But to diſpatch this chief Objection with a ſhorter word, and that ſtill taken out of their own mouths; The Pope they ſay has commanded we ſhould refuſe this Oath, but do they not too, with the ſame breath ſay, they will abſolutely forſwear obeying his Commands, if they be not preſt to renounce his Power? and what do we more than diſobey him, if notwithſtanding his Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106996:17"/> we accept of the Oath? we meddle not with his Authority, we only (as they profeſs themſelves ready to do) deny our Obedience; is it not as lawful for us, when the King commands, to admit this Oath againſt the Popes will, as for them to ſwear they'l obey the King, let the Pope command what he will?</p>
                  <p>As for our Anceſtors, had they ſeen the Unanimous Judgment of ſo many Univerſities, and the publick Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of ſo many eminent Regulars, particularly noted for great enlargers of the Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> power; had they examin'd the ſenſe of Antiquity towards Soveraign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which acknowledges them Supreme in Temporals, and accountable to none but God; had they read the learned Treatiſes compos'd by Catholick writers, both of our own and other Nations, where this King-dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power is abſolutely diſavow'd; had they perus'd the Declarations of the Kings in <hi>France,</hi> and Arreſts of Parliaments there, by which the Authors who dar'd to aſſert that Opinion were Condemn'd, and their Books burnt by the hand of the Hangman; had they done all, or any notable part of this, they could not certainly but have chang'd their Judgments, and no longer, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reaſon, Authority, and their own Intereſt, have wilfully adhered to a Tenet ſo ill grounded, and a pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice ſo ruinous.</p>
                  <p>Little of all this I fear did many of our Anceſtors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on, but guiding their Conſciences by their Ghoſtly Fathers, and their practice by their Conſciences, choſe that ſide of the Opinion, which any one might then have refus'd without Hereſy, and any one may now without ſcandal, without ſcandal I mean as to the bare Opinion conſider'd in its naked ſelf, not as it unhappily is dreſt up in the Oath, where ſome expreſſions, at firſt ſight, ſhew ſo odly, that a little prejudice or unacquaintedneſs makes many a well meaner boggle at them; And here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain I heartily renew the wiſh I have already made, that a general form of Oath, were ſo Charitably and Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendingly fram'd, as might fully ſecure to our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106996:17"/> Soveraign the Allegiance of All, and not trouble with ſcruples the leſſe inſtructed Conſcience of any.</p>
                  <p>But to diſpatch this Objection: If to take the Oath we diſcourſe of be truly juſtifiable, why may not we do what we think lawful now, becauſe our Predeceſſors did not what they thought unlawful heretofore? their Refuſal was Innocent and Laudable, ſince they follow'd ſincerely the dictates of their Conſciences; yet Ours will be <hi>neither,</hi> unleſſe we do ſo too; nay the very reaſon that made them decline the Oath, <hi>their being ſo perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> engages us to take it, if we be <hi>otherwiſe</hi> perſwaded; for, as in this all the world agrees, that an erronious Conſcience, till the miſtake be remov'd, undoubtedly obliges; ſo none will deny, but, the Truth once clear'd, the Obligation ceaſes: if ſuch then be the caſe between our Predeceſſors and Us, we may fairly be abſolv'd from following them, or rather truly be ſaid to follow them, while we all aim at the ſame end (the Conſcionable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of what we believe our Duty) though we ſeem to go thither by different ways: None but eternal truths can exact an unchangeable adherence; none but they can deſerve it.</p>
                  <p>And now I have only one Queſtion more to propoſe,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="question">
                  <head>XII. How do the Clergy, the Religious, &amp; the Wiſer ſort of the Laity in other Countries behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when the Pope makes War, or any other way Contends with their Soveraign Princes or States?</head>
                  <p>FOr even in <hi>Italy,</hi> I ſee moſt of them generally, and all of them ſometimes, diſobey the Pope, and cleave to their Country; nay thoſe very Religious who have formerly ventur'd All by a particular Obedience to his Holineſſe, are noted of late to be grown more tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate: I have read, if I miſremember not, in an It li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Author this Story, That the Pope making War ſome few years ſince, with the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106996:18"/> againſt him to the extremity of Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, occaſion'd the Duke to adviſe with his Council, how he ſhould bear himſelf towards the Church-men that liv'd in his Subjection; where after ſome debate, 'twas at length concluded, that fit perſons ſhould immediately be depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to demand of every Order both Secular and Regular, which party they intended to follow? onely to one ſort of Regulars it 'twas expreſly forbidden to make any ſuch Addreſſe, leſt their extraordinary obſequiouſneſſe to the Pope might engage them otherwiſe than the Duke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd, and the example of their Nonconformity breed a prejudice to his affairs: But they, wiſely examining the Conſequences of ſo new a Diſtinction, and the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of preventing ſo dangerous a jealouſy, did of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, without expecting any Summons, wait upon their Prince, and voluntarily preſented Him their Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proteſtations of Fidelity and Obedience: an action, which, I am apt to believe was not a little contributive to their late Reſtitution in the wary State of <hi>Venice.</hi> In fine, every ſort of Eccleſiaſticks, as well the uninvited, as the invited came in, and profeſt their firm and poſitive reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to obey the Commands of his Highneſſe, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Interdict of his Holyneſſe.</p>
                  <p>And yet (to abſtract from the Juſtice of the Quarrel, which was perhaps on the Popes ſide) the Duke is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Feudatary of the Church, but his Eſtate was at firſt deriv'd to him from the Pope, and is to return again in default of Iſſue male, which makes a fair difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Him and the Caſe of an Abſolute King.</p>
                  <p>But to look nearer home; what did we our ſelves not many years ſince in our own Country? did not almoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all the Eccleſiaſticks, and a number of the Nobility and Gentry, ſufficient to repreſent the whole little Body of Catholicks here, after full deliberation unanimouſly ſubſcribe their <hi>Negative</hi> to theſe three <hi>Articles?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p n="1">I. <hi>That the Pope or Church hath power to abſolve any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons from their Obedience to the Civil and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106996:18"/> Government eſtabliſh'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to be eſtabliſh'd in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in Civil and Political affairs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">II. <hi>That by the Command or Dispenſation of the Pope or Church, it is lawful to kill, deſtroy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or do any injury to any Perſon or Perſons living within the Kings Dominions, becauſe that ſuch a Perſon or Perſons are Accuſed, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, Cenſured, or Excommunicated for Error, Schiſm, or Hereſy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">III. <hi>That it is lawful in it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or by Diſpenſation from the Pope, to break Promiſe or Oath, made to any of the foreſaid Perſons, under pretence that they are Hereticks.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Theſe, I am ſorry I muſt confeſſe were Cenſured at <hi>Rome,</hi> privately indeed and without ſolemnity, as being perhaps either unwilling to come to the light, or unable to bear it; whatever was the motive, I cannot omit to make this Reflection upon ſo unequal a proceeding to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the proſperous <hi>French,</hi> and the afflicted <hi>Engliſh;</hi> what either of injurious or untrue, do any of theſe three Propoſitions contain, that is not both more largly, and more ſmartly expreſt in the Decrees of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and the reſt of the Univerſities cited at the beginning of this Letter? if they be free, why are not we? if we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, why are not they?</p>
                  <p>At leaſt, this Roman Cenſure of the Engliſh Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wants not ſome good effect, ſince it has abſolutely clear'd the chief remaining Objection; which elſe, if captiouſly manag'd, might perhaps have given us ſome trouble to maintain our parallel with the French, for, till then, it had been no great piece of invention, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that the Popes prohibitive Brief was applyable only to the whole Oath in groſs, and ſo might conſiſt well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough with the diſclaim of His indirect Authority over Kings; But now I ſee, 'tis not the Form, 'tis not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient Phraſe or two (the greateſt ſcruple of ſome ſerious Perſons among us here) but the very Subſtance
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106996:19"/> of the Oath, the growing denial of the Popes power to Depoſe Princes, is the chief, if not the only Scandal that's offenſive there.</p>
                  <p>Nor is this kind of diſobedience to the Popes Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands only in ſome Caſes practis'd, but by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Maxime of the Canoniſts, and of Reaſon too, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly maintain'd, both which ſtep in to our relief in ſuch extremities, and ſay, where any notable miſchief is like to follow, we are not oblig'd to obey the Pope, though he command under pain of Excommunication, <hi>ipſo facto.</hi> This is the common Opinion of the Learned; but, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis too the common ſcruple of the unlearned, I ſhall cite ſome few Authorities tranſcrib'd out of books where I find them collected, having my ſelf neither skill nor delight in ſuch kind of Studies; Of theſe I conceive two or three, in a point ſo evident, abundantly ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; One is of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> 3. thus cited by <hi>Franc. Zabarel de ſchiſmat. Papae non eſt obediendum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We are not to obey the Pope when there is a vehement preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the ſtate of the Church may be diſturb'd, or other miſchiefs like to follow; Nay it were a ſin to obey, becauſe every one is bound to prevent future evils.</hi> Conformable to this, <hi>Sylveſter</hi> alleging <hi>Panormitan,</hi> ſays, <hi>Verb. obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientia Num. 5. Nec eſt ei obedientium,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We are not to obey the Pope; if our obedience may be preſumed will trouble the ſtate of the Church, or be cauſe of any future E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or Scandal, though the Precept were under pain of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication,</hi> Latae ſententiae. And <hi>Cardinal Tolet</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame Authors, pronounces the ſame truth in far more ample terms.</p>
                  <p>Do not theſe Authors (and none I ſuppoſe, for I have not much acquaintance with that ſort of Learning, can differ from them in proper Caſes) give us indeed more than we have need of? Are not the Conſequences of our obeying the Pope's Letters, ruinous to our Fortunes; and which is worſe, Scandalous to our Religion? ſhall we not ſtrengthen the ſuſpition of our Factiouſneſſe, and Inconſiſtency with Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106996:19"/> and can a little Credit of a few at <hi>Rome,</hi> counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiſe a burthen that lies ſo heavy on us all, in our own Country.</p>
                  <p>The Circumſtances we are in, I confeſſe, are very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, when the wiſeſt of thoſe who ſhould adviſe us, are not fully free to ſpeak their thoughts? but by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Concernments ſo tempted to comply, that nothing but a rare Sincerity and Courage can enable them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; a Caſe that needs indeed ſome pity, but deſerves no praiſe: and therefore as we ſhall be to blame, if we Cenſure too readily the Effects of Frailty in Them, ſo will they be leſs Innocent, if they Condemn too ſeverely the Uſe of Liberty in Us. For my part, I have this to ſay, in proof of my own Indifferency, I am not Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious for preferment from Any, but humbly and heartily acknowledge my ſubmiſſion to every one above me; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to the two Supreme, whom with all fidelity I am ready to obey, as my Soveragin Governors, though They never ſhould be my particular Benefactors.</p>
                  <p>A Duty we owe to the Pope, a Duty to the King; both commanded by God, both obliging under Sin; yet both confin'd to their proper limits; Too much of the Temporal may be aſcrib'd to Popes; too much of the Spiritual to Kings: too much may be challeng'd by Both: the difficulty is, when either exceeds, who muſt be Judge: if the cauſe be clearly Temporal, 'tis clearly the King (ſpeaking of Common Right, not their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Agreements) if Spiritual, the Pope: but where the Quality of the cauſe is invincibly doubted, (which can ſeldome be without a ſtrange paſſion at leaſt on one ſide,) I know no Judge expreſly impower'd to decide ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary a Queſtion, nor can imagin any other remedy, than what true Reaſon, preſs'd with neceſſity, will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporally dictate in ſuch an occaſion. However, thus far I plainly ſee, that, as ſometimes a miſchance may happen by the Competition of theſe two Authorities, ſo often very many and great advantages may accrue to Both, by their good correſpondence, and mutual aſſiſtance.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106996:20"/>
                  <p>But by no means can I ſee, were the Extent of the Popes power in Spirituals, and the Denyal of his power in Temporals well underſtood, what diſturbance He could poſſibly make in this Kingdome? if he excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the <hi>Protestants,</hi> they little regard it: if the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> ſuch as are rightly inſtructed know their Civil Obligations both to their King and Fellow-ſubjects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main entirely the ſame after Excommunication as they were before. No Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures againſt a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> here altering in the leaſt tittle his Circumſtances to <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> ſince of its own nature, it only concerns Communication in Spirituals, wherein, before any Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they no more Communicate together, than after: indeed among the <hi>Catholicks</hi> ſuch Cenſure has ſome effect; yet of it ſelf, only thus far can it work with them, to ſuſpend or deprive their Communion in Holy Offices; to which, if any Temporal prejudices be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd (as that an Excommunicate cannot bring an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.) they wholy are deriv'd from the Civil Power, and when it ſees convenient may wholy be revok'd.</p>
                  <p>As for the particular Laws of our Country, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the unhappy dividing times of <hi>H.</hi> 8. our Wiſe, yet Pious Aunceſtors fail'd not to provide for the publick peace againſt all Forein incroachments; prohibiting the importation of any <hi>Bull</hi> from <hi>Rome</hi> without his Majeſties allowance, and impoſing penalties on any that preſum'd without His Royal Aſſent to publiſh them. And were things ſo diſpos'd that the little correſpondence which is neceſſary for Catholicks here with <hi>Rome</hi> were <hi>regulated,</hi> and not by ſeverities endeavour'd to be <hi>extinguiſh'd,</hi> (which cannot be effected without extinguiſhing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelf) I am confident no one ſort of people in the whole Nation would be either more faithfully ſerviceable to their King, or more ſecurely incapable of diſserving their Country. Nor would this deſign require any more conſideration than only to reſolve that their Eccleſiaſtical Government ſhould be no other than ſuch as had known Rules &amp; Limits, not Arbitrarily depending on <hi>Rome;</hi> And
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106996:20"/> their Eccleſiaſtical Governours no other than ſuch as were of known Loyalty to their King, and Piety to their Country.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>Thus Sir I have finiſh'd theſe few Queſtions; and hope by Your inſtruction to ſettle my mind: profeſſing hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my abſolute readineſſe (with the Grace of God) to govern my Underſtanding by Reaſon, and my Actions by my Underſtanding: only this ſhort Petition I Humbly add, That as your Nature is Frank and Generous, your Anſwer may be Manly and Candid, not in the way miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call'd <hi>Pious,</hi> but with a ſtrict Conformity to what is true and ſolid; and however your Opinion may poſſibly in ſome things differ from mine, yet ſtill continue in all things to Command</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  <signed>Your Moſt Humble Servant A. G.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>St. Georges Day, 1661</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. Line 27. Dele. <hi>for.</hi> Page 4. Line 17. read <hi>Depoſe.</hi> And Line 25. read <hi>Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
